Sync & corrections by Elderfel
www.addic7ed.com
쿵푸에선 이렇게 말한다
In kung fu, we say...
"One hand lies...
한 손은 거짓말을 하고...
다른 손은 진실을 말한다
...the other hand tells the truth."
다시 하죠
Try that again.
네가 어느 날
서방으로 돌아갔을 때
If you, one day,
make it back to the West...
사람들에게 '쿵푸'라는
낯선 단어를 어찌 설명하겠느냐?
what will you tell men
of this strange word, "kung fu"?
Will you tell them that it means to fight?
싸우는 방법이라고
설명할 것이냐?
아니면...
Or will you say...
소림사의 승려처럼...
like a monk from Shaolin...
to summon the spirit...
학과 호랑이의
영혼을 부르는 것이라
말하겠느냐!
of the crane and the tiger?
쿵푸(功夫)
Kung fu.
이것은 '노력에서 얻어낸
뛰어난 기술'을 말함이다
It means, "supreme skill from hard work."
위대한 시인은
쿵푸에 도달하였다
A great poet has reached kung fu.
화가, 서예가...
The painter, the calligrapher...
그들도 쿵푸를 가졌다
말할 수 있다
they can be said to have kung fu.
심지어 요리사도
계단을 비로 쓰는 사람도...
Even the cook,
the one who sweeps steps...
능수능란한 하인도...
or a masterful servant...
쿵푸를 가졌다 할 수 있다
can have kung fu.
연습, 준비
Practice. Preparation...
끊임없는 반복...
endless repetition.
정신이 지치고
몸이 아파올 때까지
Until your mind is weary,
and your bones ache.
땀을 흘리기에도
피곤하고...
Until you're too tired to sweat...
숨쉬기조차 지칠 때까지...
too wasted to breathe.
그것만이, 그 길만이
That is the way, the only way...
one acquires kung fu.
쿵푸를 얻는 방법이다
소년아, 애석하게도...
Unfortunately, boy...
you have not.
넌 아직이다
이제까지 내가 본
가장 두려운 군대다!
A more fearsome army, I have never seen!
It is no wonder the barbarians fled.
야만인들이 도망친
이유가 있도다!
하지만...
Yet...
그대들의 재상의
이목을 끄는 것이 있다
it has come to the attention
of your Chancellor...
그 군인 중 몇몇이 송 조정의
질서에 의문을 표했다 한다
that some of his soldiers have questioned
the political order of the Song court...
now that the Emperor
has passed beyond our world.
폐하께서 승하하셨으니
더할 것이다
장군
General.
장군의 휘하 중 가장
용맹한 전사가 누구요?
Who is the most supreme fighter
within your ranks?
Yang Chun.
양춘!
산둥 성에서 이자는
In Shantung Province, he is known as...
선풍호(旋風虎)라 불렸습니다
"Whirlwind Tiger."
소림 5권을 모두 익혔습니다
He has mastered the
Five Animal Styles of Shaolin.
송조 만세 만세 만만세!
May Song dynasty endure 10,000 years!
그대들은 '귀뚜라미 재상'의
사마귀 놀이를 무엇이라 하는가?
What do the men say about your
Cricket Minister's praying mantis games?
겸손과 존경의 뜻으로
With humility and respect...
몇몇이 재상님의
곤충 놀이를...
some have spoken of
the Chancellor's insect games as a...
별난 취미라 하였습니다
curious hobby.
그것 뿐입니다, 재상님
Those were the only words whispered,
My Chancellor.
어디 한 번 보자
Demonstrate...
풍호라는 이름이
왜 유명한 것인지
why the name Whirlwind Tiger is so famous.
날 물리치면 지휘관으로
승격될 것이며
Defeat me,
and you are promoted to a command post
그에 따른 부대 수익과
여흥도 얻을 것이다
with all its residual income
and pleasures.
하지만 그대가
날 물리치면
However... should I defeat you...
내 시종이 되어야 한다
you are my chamber boy.
당랑권이다
Praying Mantis Kung Fu.
별난 취미라고?
Curious little hobby?
아리크는 내 동생이지만
Ariq was my brother.
반역자이기도 했다
But he was a traitor.
이제 그는 죽었다
Now, he is dead.
그의 머리를 베고
그의 피로 땅을 적셨다
I took his head,
soaked the earth with his blood...
그를 동생으로 사랑했으나
반역자로서 죽였다
I loved him as a brother,
but I killed him as a traitor.
내 마음과
우리의 법으로...
In my heart and by our laws...
그것이 필요했으며
공정했다고 본다
I know this to be necessary and just.
내 행동에 반대하는 자는
지금 자유롭게 말하라
Those who disagree with my actions,
speak now without repercussion.
이것이 내 동생을 입에 올린
마지막이 될 것이다
That is the last
we shall speak of my brother.
오촌 카이두가 그의 땅과
Cousin Kaidu will inherit his lands,
그의 군대와 백성을
물려받을 것이다
his armies, his people.
이제...
Now...
as to the war deferred
with the Song rebels...
미뤄둔 송 반란군과의
전쟁 말인데...
우창 전투에서
치욕을 당했습니다
We were dishonored
at the Battle of Wuchang.
귀뚜라미 재상이 혹독한
댓가를 치르게 해야 합니다
We must visit hell
upon the Cricket Minister.
With respect to my cousin, Jingim...
진금 황자께는 죄송하지만...
칸께서 직접 나서셔야 할 것입니다
the Khan must now assert his dominion.
우리 군은?
Our forces?
카라코룸의 군대가
완전히 정비되면...
With Karakorum's men
finally standing ready...
- 강한 두 군대를 가지게 되십니다
- 셋입니다
- you are two armies strong.
- Three.
서쪽의 군대도 전투에
대비하였습니다, 대칸
The armies of the West
are prepared for battle, Great Khan.
대칸의 명령을 기다립니다
We await your command.
생각할 것이 많다
I have much to think on.
대칸이시여
Great Khan...
내일 저녁 제 주둔지에서 열...
Tomorrow evening,
at my encampment, if I may...
칸께 바치는 연회에
I invite you to a feast...
in your honor.
와 주셨으면 합니다
가겠다, 카이두
고맙네
I will attend, Kaidu.
Thank you.
송의 재상이 보낸
공물입니다, 대칸
A tribute from the Song Chancellor,
Great Khan.
우창에서 우리가 잡은
송의 포로는 몇명이냐?
How many Song prisoners
did we take at Wuchang?
열명 남짓입니다, 아버님
A mere dozen, Father.
그들의 사지를 갈갈이 찢어
시다오에게 보내십시오, 폐하
Rip their bodies asunder, Sire.
Send Sidao their parts.
재무상, 이 용감한 전사들의
신원을 밝히고
My Minister of Finance,
identify these brave warriors.
재무성에서 가족에게
헌사를 내리도록 하라
See their families receive
tribute from the treasury.
그것이 그대의 일이다
That is your place.
그러겠습니다, 폐하
It will be done, Sire.
칸을 모시는 것은
단순한 영광이 아니라
To service the Khan
is not merely an honor...
축복이다
it is a blessing.
이 세상에서 칸의 성욕을
충족시키는 사람은...
To be sure, those who satisfy the
Lord Khan's carnal needs here on Earth...
will be granted supreme favor
in the next life.
내세에 큰 복을
받을 것이며
As well as 20 karats of gold.
순금도 하사받을 것이다
왕실 후궁에 의해
검사받을 것이다
You will be tested
by the royal concubines.
성욕의 기술을 가장 능히
익힌 사람은
The most proficient in the art of arousal
will earn the privilege
우리 대칸의
오욕의 방에
of residing permanently here...
영원히 남는
특권을 누릴 것이다
in our Great Khan's
Hall of Five Desires.
영원히라는 말은
말 그대로다
By "permanently,"
I mean just that.
선택된 후
왕족을 모실 때까지
If selected, you will remain
in the Hall of Five Desires
오욕의 방에 남게 된다
until released from royal service.
왕실 후궁으로
간택되면...
If you are chosen
to become a Royal Concubine...
모든 것들을
얻을 것이다
all needs will be met.
선택받지 않으면
재무상에게 인도되어
Those not chosen will be delivered
to the Ministry of Finance
칸의 조정에 넘겨질 것이다
to be sold off to the Khan's court.
조정에서도 선택되지 못하면
캄불락 밖의 사창가에 가게 된다
Those unclaimed by the court will be
sold to whorehouses in outer Cambulac.
그대들의 삶이 달린 것처럼
최선을 다하라
Perform as though
your life depends upon it.
삶이 달린 것이 맞으니
It most likely does.
기수여, 앉으시게
Horseman. Sit.
I'm in a hurry.
- 바쁩니다
- 앉으라 했소
I said sit.
Business done quickly
is business done badly.
서둘러 일을 처리하면
잘 처리되는 법이 없지
잘 처리하고 싶지 않은가?
Do you want me to do bad business, hmm?
여기
There.
눈에는 눈이라
Eyeball to eyeball.
자, 이제 거래를 하든지...
Now, we can either deal...
아니면 꺼지시오
or fuck.
그대 선택이오
Your choice.
그대 손실이야
Your loss.
오팔과 은이오
It's opal and silver.
And?
그래서
Last time, you gave me twice that.
지난번엔 이것보다
두 배를 줬었소
이번달은 좀 안 좋았어
I had bad month.
기다려, 유럽인
Hold, Europa.
여기 무슨 일로 왔나?
What's your business here?
돈 가진 손님이오
비키시오
I'm a customer with coin.
Let me pass.
이보시오
Hey.
Where is the man
who owns the bay gelding outside?
밖에 매여있는
말 주인이 누굽니까?
Go ask the horse, Latin.
말한테 물어봐, 라틴인
초원이 오늘밤엔
달고 시원했어, 자빙
The grassland was
sweet and cool tonight, Za Bing.
내 고향 같았어
So much like my old home.
그자의 고향과도
비슷하겠죠
And so much like his.
오늘은 어떤 보물을
남기고 오셨습니까?
What treasure
did you leave for him this night?
물어보지 말아야 하는 거 알텐데
You know better than to ask.
제 무지는 절 지킬 만큼
깊지 않습니다
My ignorance is not deep enough
to protect me.
그 무뢰배가 공주님을
지킬 것이란 믿음도 없고요
And I do not trust the scoundrel
to protect you.
툴가는 날 해치지 않을 거야
Tulga would not hurt me.
보석을 계속
준다면 말입니다
As long as the jewels come.
나와 함께 하겠다는
희망을 품는 한 말이야
As long as he harbors hope to be with me.
그 고리는 약해질 겁니다, 코카친
그러면 공주님을 폭로할 것입니다
That tether will weaken, Kokachin.
And he will expose you.
멈추셔야 합니다
This must stop.
그대는 누굴 섬기는가?
Whom do you serve?
이 일은 그만 거론하자
We speak of this no more.
그리고 두려워 할 필요 없어
And you have nothing to fear.
That is precisely what I am bid to do.
Fear.
두려워하는 것이
바로 제가 명령받은 것입니다
I must protect you.
전 공주님을 지켜야 합니다
그대가 날 지키면
And as you protect me...
I will protect you,
나도 그대를 지킬 것이다, 자빙
Za Bing.
이 세상에서 내 편은
그대 뿐이다
You're my only friend in this world.
Sunflower?
해바라기야
네 하인은 어디 있느냐?
Where is your servant?
아침 식사에
수행하러 갔어요
Attending to my breakfast.
그렇구나, 재밌게 놀렴
Excellent. Enjoy.
Why would he summon me?
날 왜 보자고 하실까요?
내 생각은 말이다
My suspicion?
Yes?
네
네가 네 질문의 답을
찾을 것 같구나
Is that you will discover
the answer to your question...
머지 않아 말이다
rather soon.
그 깊은 통찰력으로
다른 문제에 대한 생각도 주시죠
Perhaps you might lend your
venerable insight to another query.
I would rather enjoy my wine.
그냥 내 술을 즐기겠다
바야우트 부족은
어떤 자들입니까?
The Bayaut tribe. Who are they?
네 질문의 의도를 알겠구나
조심히 행동해라, 폴로 공
I grasp the spirit of your question.
Tread carefully, Master Polo.
그 부모, 형제, 부족민...
Her parents, siblings, countrymen...
칸의 의지에 복종하지 않아
참수당했다
they were slaughtered
for refusing to bend to the Khan's will.
청공주는 그 일족의
유일한 생존자다
The Blue Princess is the last of her clan.
어떻게 살아남은 겁니까?
How did she survive?
왕족이라 가치가 있거든
Her royal blood is valued.
정치적 거래로
팔려나갈 운명이다
She is destined to be sold
for political currency.
Steer your eyes from her visage.
그 얼굴에서
눈을 돌리거라
She is beyond your reach.
네가 탐할 수 없는 사람이다
그렇게 말하더군요
So I've been told.
부르셨습니까, 폐하
You called for me, Sire?
형제가 있느냐?
Do you have brothers?
있었으면 했습니다
I wish I had.
같이 놀 사람 말입니다
Someone to play with.
뭔갈 같이 할 사람 말이지
Someone to conspire with.
형제는...
Brothers...
때로는 축복이고
때로는 저주다
Sometime blessing, sometime curse.
그대들의 성경 이야기처럼 말이다
Like those in your holy book.
Cain and Abel?
카인과 아벨 말씀입니까?
Tell me of them.
그들에 대해 말해보라
아담의 아들들입니다
Sons of Adam.
카인이 먼저 태어났으며
Cain was the first man to be born.
아벨이 먼저 죽었습니다
Abel, the first to die.
형제의 칼에 죽었지?
By the blade of his brother, yes?
아벨에 대한 신의 사랑을 질투하여
Envious of God's love for Abel,
카인은 동생을 죽여
그 시체를 숨기고
Cain killed his brother,
concealed his body...
신께 거짓말을 하였습니다
and lied to the Lord above.
살인자는 어떻게 되었느냐?
What became of the murderer?
그는 카인의 낙인을 지니고
He bore the mark of Cain...
세계를 떠돌았습니다
and was cursed to roam the Earth.
끊임없이요
Endlessly.
오늘까지?
To this day?
아닙니다, 떠돌다가
더 이상 갈 곳이 없자
No. He wandered until
he could wander no more.
아내를 얻고
집을 지었고
So, he took a wife, built a house...
집이 무너져 깔려 죽을 때까지
그곳에서 살았습니다
and lived there until it collapsed
and crushed him dead.
누군가는 지어낸 이야기일
뿐이라고 합니다
Some say this is an invented story,
nothing more.
더 중요한 가르침을
주기 위해서라고요
Meant to impart a greater lesson.
Which is?
그것이 무엇인가?
The scholars and historians
of Venice are superior
베니스의 학자와 역사가는
세계 어느 곳의
누구보다 더 뛰어납니다
to all others across the land.
전 그 물음을 탐색할
지식을 얻지 못했습니다
I have not the studies
to begin to explore such questions.
Try.
한번 해 보라
형제의 물건을 탐하는 것은
인간의 본성이 아닙니다
It is in our nature to seek
our brother's possessions.
그것을 얻기 위해
죽이고자 하는 것도 마찬가집니다
And be willing to destroy to obtain them.
누구보다 뛰어나다고?
Superior to all others, hmm?
다른 뜻으로 한 말은...
I did not mean to offend...
오늘 밤 내 오촌 카이두의
연회에 참석하라
You shall attend
my cousin Kaidu's feast tonight.
덜 발달된 문화에 대한
네 생각을 듣겠다
I await your thoughts on a lesser culture.
여섯이라고?
Six of them?
가장 어린 자는
16살이었습니다
The youngest was 16.
Maidar's boy. Taban.
마이다의 아들인
타반입니다
타반
Taban.
내가 마이다에게
몇 번을 말했는데...
How many times had I told Maidar...
아직 전쟁에 나갈
준비가 안 됐다고...
he was not prepared for war.
Like you, as a boy,
his head was always in numbers.
네가 어릴 때처럼 그 애 머리도
온통 숫자로만 가득차 있었어
And now it's in a thatched trunk.
이젠 짚으로 삼은 상자에
담겨 있지요
Ahmad. Please.
아마드, 제발
용서하십시오, 황후마마
My apologies, Empress.
마이다에게
은궤를 보내도록 해라
Send Maidar a purse of silver.
이미 처리했습니다
It is done.
The Khan commanded gold.
칸께서는 금을
내리라 하셨는데요
인상적이군요
Impressive.
I will not choose my husband's concubines
based upon Shria's judgment.
내 남편의 후궁을 고르는 데
이슬람인의 판단에 따를 순 없지
강아지가 얼굴을 핥는데
창백해지는 것도 봤다
I've seen her faint
when a puppy licked her face.
Well...
뭐...
that's no puppy.
강아지가 아니지 않습니까
벌써 셈을 하고 있느냐, 아마드?
Have you already taken tally, Ahmad?
사창가에 팔아넘기기 전에
Perhaps you'll add that one to your harem
네 할렘에 더하는 것이 어떠하냐?
before selling
the castoffs to the brothels?
칸의 이익이 되고
재정에 보탬이 되는 것을
Whatever turns profits
for the Khan and fills a treasury...
지켜보는 것 뿐입니다
I will oversee.
그게 네 일이지
As is your duty.
그렇죠
Yes.
하지만 그 이유로
온 게 아닙니다
But not why I come to you.
제가 자격이 없는 것도 알고
I know it's not my place, and...
그 선을 넘고싶은
마음은 없으나...
I do not wish to overstep my bounds.
넌 칸에게나 나에게나
아들과 같다
You are as a son to the Khan and to me.
말하기 두려워할 필요가 없다
You need not hold your tongue.
Have you any insight
into the Khan's private thoughts?
칸이 어떤 생각을 하시는지
혹시 아시고 계십니까?
무엇에 대해 말이냐?
Concerning?
쓰레기 지아 시다오를
없애는 것 말입니다
Spilling the blood of that savage,
Jia Sidao.
증오가 증오로
없어지진 않는다
Hatred does not cease by hatred.
창으로 멈출 수는 있습니다
But it may be stopped by a saber.
그 창은 결국 자신에게
돌아오게 돼 있다
Until they eventually
turn the saber back on you.
재정의 문제냐, 아마드?
Are these matters of finance, Ahmad?
Finance fuels the crucible of war...
재정은 전쟁을 더욱 부추깁니다
그 전리품은 재무를
살찌우지요
and its spoils fill our treasury.
같은 것이죠
They are one and the same.
Why speak of this to me?
Why not Yusuf?
왜 내게 이걸 말하느냐?
유세프가 아니고?
The Khan's ear opens widest
for you, Empress.
칸께선 황후의 말씀에
가장 귀기울이십니다
You are a magician.
마법사 같아요
You are certain to be selected.
분명히 간택될 거에요
목욕을 위해
정화의 방으로 모여라
Report to the Hall of Purification
for cleansing.
잠깐
Stop.
머리카락을 들어봐라
Lift up your hair.
Sit.
앉아라
링은 언제 만났소?
When did you meet Ling?
태어난 지 3일 된 날
그애를 안아 보았습니다
I held her on her third day.
내 여동생은
어찌 알고 지내셨소?
How did you come to know my sister?
같이 몸을 팔았군
You whored together.
메이린은 내 친구였습니다
Mei Lin was my friend.
'재상님'
Chancellor.
지금 생활에 만족하시오?
Do you enjoy your current station in life?
후궁 생활 말이오
As concubine?
Yes... Chancellor.
네, 재상님
자유롭게 말해도 좋소
You may speak freely.
진심입니다,재상님
I do, Chancellor.
It seems to me
that yours is the work of animals.
내가 보기엔 그대의 일이
동물의 일처럼 느껴지오
기본적인 욕구를 충족시키긴 하나
그럴 가치는 없지
I see no worth in it,
as it speaks to our most base instincts.
하지만 내 생각에
몇몇은 태어날 때 얻은
But I suppose some in life must make do
변변찮은 재능으로도
먹고 살아야 했을 거요
with the meager skills
birth has bestowed upon them.
그건 내가 뭐라할 건 아니지
I make no judgment, of course.
참 아름다우시오
You are quite stunning.
전엔 못 알아봤소
I never took notice.
운명이 그대에게 달려 있소
Providence is upon you.
이제 냄새나는 살덩어리에
깔리는 일은 없을 것이오
Your days will not be spent pinned
beneath stinking flesh on the floor.
그대는 내 여동생의 전각에
매일 들어서
You are to report every morning
to my sister's chambers
내 조카를 돌보시게
to care for my niece.
What you do with your nights
is entirely of your choosing.
밤엔 무엇을 하든지
그대의 맘이오
You are excused.
물러가시게
아니야
No.
몇살인가?
How old?
Nineteen.
19살입니다
이 아이의 가족은?
What of this one's family?
아비가 장벽 넘어
소금광산에서 일합니다
Her father works in
the salt mines beyond the Wall.
이 아이는
And her?
아비가 우창에서
죽었습니다, 마마
Father died at Wuchang, Empress.
그 전엔?
Before that?
도공이었습니다
He was a potter.
너 말고
Not you.
너
You.
안 됩니다, 마마
절 뽑으셔야...
No, Empress, please, you must...
"Must"?
뽑으셔야?
칸에게 바칠 아이는 여기까지다
That is all for the Khan.
가서 옷을 입히거라
Take them to be dressed.
Do you attend the feast?
연회에 참석하십니까?
오늘 내 머리나 마음이나
아라그가 당기질 않는다
My head and my heart
do not yearn for airag this evening.
미령한 데가 있으십니까, 폐하?
Are you unwell, Sire?
간단한 질문인데
대답은 복잡하겠구나
A complicated answer
to a simple question.
진금 왕자가
대리로 갈 것이다
Prince Jingim will stand proxy.
What do you make of the boy?
그 아이는 어떻게 생각하느냐?
- 후계자로 말입니까?
- 아니, 왕자 말고 라틴인 말이다
As heir?
No, not that one. The Latin.
그 아이는...
통찰력이 있고
He appears... insightful...
열정적이며
무모하기도 합니다
Passionate... reckless.
그 아이가 칸국에 쓸모가 있을지는
시간이 지나야 알 것입니다
Time will determine
if he will be of use to the Khanate.
그래
Hmm.
좋은 밤 되십시오
Good night.
어서 오시게
Greetings.
잘 오셨소
Welcome, cousin.
돼지 20마리, 염소 30마리
영양 열 마리 정도를 잡아 구웠고
We've slaughtered 20 pigs, 30 goats,
and a dozen antelope for the fire...
며칠간 마실 술도
넉넉히 준비하였소
prepared wine and nermel for days.
칸의 일행은 언제 도착하오?
When does the Khan's party arrive?
우리는 시작할 준비가 되었소
My men are ready to commence.
술을 따르시죠
Pour the drink.
칸이 오시기 전에
연회를 여는 건 결례요
To begin before the Khan arrives
would be a great dishonor.
칸께서 다른 일 때문에
못 오신 거요?
The Lord Khan
had other matters to attend to?
통풍이 도졌습니다
사과의 말씀과 함께 날 보내셨습니다
Hobbled by gout...
he sends his regrets, and me in his stead.
그럼 우창에서 우리 전사를 이끈
장군께 경의를 표하도록 하지요
Then let us honor the General
who led our warriors at Wuchang.
말을 받아드릴까요, 폴로 공?
May I take your horse, Master Polo?
화살과 창은
참을 수 있지만
Arrows and sabers, I can withstand.
이 통풍은...
But the gout...
영원한 푸른 하늘의 저주요
it's a curse from the Eternal Blue Sky.
That...
그것도 있고...
- and an excess of wine.
- Yeah...
- 술을 많이 마시기도 하시고요
- 그렇지
긴장을 많이 하셨습니다, 폐하
So much tension, husband.
할아버지께서
내가 잘 때 오셔서
Grandfather appeared to me whilst I slept.
본인과 함께 왕국을
걷자고 하셨지
Urged me to walk the kingdom with him...
and gout wouldn't let me take a step.
그런데 통풍 때문에
한 발짝도 못 걸었소
칭기스께선
날 비웃으시곤
Genghis laughed at me.
혼자서 떠나셨소
He went off on his own.
The Great Genghis
did not have a brother like Ariq.
위대한 칭기스께는 아리크와
같은 형제가 없었습니다
칸에겐 거리낌도 후회도
없어야 하오
A Khan has no qualms or regrets.
아마드가 제게 말하더군요
Ahmad spoke to me.
전쟁이 답이라고 했습니다
He thinks war is the answer.
왜 아마드가 그대에게
전쟁 이야길 하오?
Why does Ahmad speak to you of war?
그는 신임받는 재상이고
저는 황후 아닙니까?
He is a trusted minister.
I am his Queen.
그의 칸이 진정한 결정을 내릴지
의심이 많아 보이는군
He has much doubt
his Khan will make the true decision.
그대를 이용해 내 마음을
흔들려 했던 거요
He wanted to use you to sway my mind.
그럼 사람을 잘못 찾았군요
Well, he clearly came to the wrong person.
그렇지
Hmm.
놈의 불알을 길고양이에게
던져줘야 했었는데
I should feed his balls to feral cats.
He takes liberties with his station.
자기 마음대로
바꾸려고 하다니...
폐하를 위하고 폐하께
최선이 되는 것을 바라는 겁니다
He defends you
and wants only the best for you.
아리크의 죽음이 불러올
결과를 걱정하는 겁니다
He worries what may come
in the wake of Ariq's death.
그대는 내게 동생을
죽이라 하지 않았소
You counseled me to kill my brother.
그랬지요
그건 잘 한 겁니다
I did and I did it well.
Now, you must consider
all roads before you.
이제 폐하 앞에 있는 모든 길을
생각하셔야 합니다
하지만 생각하는 데만
시간을 쏟아선 안 됩니다
But the journey must not linger
in the deliberation.
어느 길로 가야 하는지
그대도 나름 생각이 있는 것 같군
I can only assume you have an opinion
as to which road must be taken.
노여움 대신 지혜를 택하십시오
Choose wisdom over wrath.
폐하 자신과 폐하의 군대
백성 간의 균열을 치유하십시오
Heal any rifts within yourself,
your armies, your people.
성벽 도시는
계속 버틸 것이나...
The Walled City will continue to stand...
폐하가 택하신 때에
무너질 것입니다
only to fall at a time of your choosing.
그대 이야기를 많이 들었다
I have heard much of you.
마르코 폴로
Marco... Polo.
무슨 뜻인가?
What does that mean?
위대한 탐험가란 뜻이오
"The Great Explorer."
아니
No.
내 생각에 그 이름은...
I think it means...
창백한 꽃 같다
"Pale Flower."
꽃이요?
"Flower"?
그대는...
You look...
건드리기에도 약해보인다
delicate to the touch.
전장에서 수백명을 죽인 몸이오
I have killed hundreds of men in battle.
창백한 꽃에 가시가 없단
말은 하지 않았다
I didn't say the Pale Flower
didn't have thorns.
몽골인의 화살보다
더 날카롭소
Sharper than a Mongolian's arrow.
내가 두려워해야 하는가?
Should I be afraid?
Only if you insult me.
날 모욕하면요
그러면...
Then...
내 말을 조심해야겠군
I must watch my words.
그럼 그대가 정복한 여자들은...
And the women you have conquered.
그대의 손에서 녹아내리던가?
Did they melt in your hands?
Like snow in the desert.
마치 사막의 눈처럼요
그럼 내게 해 보게
Take me in your hands.
그것 말고
Not that.
베네치아에서도
씨름은 하겠지?
Do you wrestle in Venice?
그럼요
Of course.
보여줘
Show me.
- 다치게 하고 싶지 않소
- 그래?
- I don't want to hurt you.
- Oh. Mmm?
신이 항상 우리를 지켜보신다면...
If the Gods are always watching...
we might as well put on a good show.
즐길 만한 광경을
보여주는 게 낫겠지요
잠이 들지 못하는 것은
나이드는 것의 저주요...
The inability to sleep
is the curse of the aged...
죄책감의 저주입니다
and the guilty.
통풍 때문이기도 하지
And the gout- stricken.
용서하십시오
Pardon me.
어리석게도 폐하께서
I foolishly assumed
동생의 머리가 땅에 뒹굴고
시체가 동물의 먹이가 된 걸
you were dreaming about
your brother's head rolling in the dirt...
his body, a feast for vultures.
생각하셨다 여겼습니다
저들이 나를 미워할까?
Do they hate me?
폐하의 진짜 모습을
미워하는 것이
It is better to be
hated for what you are
than to be loved for what you are not.
폐하의 거짓된 모습을
사랑하는 것보다 낫습니다
You're a drunken fool.
술취한 바보 같으니
So, kill me.
그럼 절 죽이시지요
생각해 보았다
I have thought about it.
잠이 들고 싶으시지요
But you wish to sleep.
그대가 내게 그 지긋지긋한
한족 스승에 대해
I know you want to tell me
one of those endless stories
끝없는 이야기를
말하고 싶은 건 안다
from that infernal
Chinese teacher of yours.
오늘은 아닙니다, 폐하
No stories tonight, Sire.
선 수수께끼도?
No Zen riddles?
대신 진실을 말씀드리지요
I will offer a truth instead.
아리크를 살렸다면...
Had you spared Ariq...
다른 반역자들이
일어났을 것입니다
you would have encouraged other traitors.
그의 처형은 공정했다
His execution was just.
아니죠, 하지만 필요하였습니다
No. But it was necessary...
폐하의 제국을
보전하기 위해서는요
in that moment,
to preserve your Empire.
그대는 걱정 하나를 누그러뜨리고
더 큰 걱정을 불러일으키는구나
You ease one worry,
but aggravate one greater.
As life is wont to do.
삶이 그러하지요
- 입 열어
- 싫어요!
- Open your mouth!
- No, no, no, no, no.
- 열라고!
- 싫어요!
- Open it!
- No, no!
닫아!
Shut it!
말해보게, 마르코
Tell us, Marco.
그대들의 연회도
이에 비할만 한가?
Do your feasts compare to this?
다릅니다
They are different.
여기서 우리는 돼지고기를 먹고
Here, we eat the pig.
베네치아에서는
돼지와 춤을 추겠죠
In Venice, they dance with it.
If the Venetian feasts were comparable,
why would our friend leave home?
베네치아의 연회가 이에 비할 만하다면
우리 친구가 왜 고향을 떠났겠습니까?
우리는 가면을 씁니다
We wear masks.
무엇 때문에?
For what purpose?
가면은 억압된 것에서
자유롭게 해 주지요
The mask frees us of inhibitions.
그래서 도살업자가
상인의 딸과 잠자리를 하고
And the butcher
beds the merchant's daughter...
while his wife beds the gardener.
그 아내는 정원사와
잠자리를 하지요
가면으로 수치스러움을 막는 겁니다
The mask prevents embarrassment.
흥미롭군
Interesting.
우리 장군 중 몇몇도
나중에 가면을 써야 하겠군
Perhaps, some of our generals
should wear masks in the future.
수치스럽지 않으려면 말이야
To prevent embarrassment.
우리에겐 역사상 전 세계에서
가장 위대한 장군들이 있소
We have the greatest generals in the world
and all of history.
우리는 우창에서
이길 수 있었을 것이오
We would have been victorious at Wuchang
had Genghis Khan
or our Lord Kublai commanded.
칭기스칸이나 쿠빌라이 칸께서
지휘하셨다면 말이오
I prefer a general
with aggression in his blood
저는 장군이라면 그 피에
용맹함이 흘러야 한다 봅니다
말 위에서 앞일에 대한
두려움으로 벌벌 떨기보다는요
to one who quakes with trepidation
on his steed.
난 순혈 몽골인을 원하네
I prefer a pure general.
A Mongol, raised Mongol...
몽골인로 태어나
몽골인으로 자라고
칭기스가 흘린 피로 목욕하고
그의 길을 숭상해야지
bathed in the blood spilt by Genghis,
steeped in his ways.
A warrior like you, Byamba.
Untainted.
비얌바 자네처럼
때묻지 아니한
순수한 몽골 남자 말일세
A true Mongol. A man.
아니면 여자이든가
Or woman.
칸께선 우리 조언에
귀기울이셨소?
Has the Khan heeded our counsel?
칸께선 그 스스로의
의지대로 움직이십니다
Our Khan has a will of his own.
실패했을 경우 그 의지가
큰 화가 될 것이오
It is a will that may break
if he fails to act.
We will support and reinforce his will,
whatever it might be.
우린 그분의 의지가 무엇이든
지지하고 강화할 것입니다
그래야지요, 재상
Of course, Minister.
다른 뜻이 있는 건 아니오
I would never suggest otherwise.
그분은 내 칸이시오
He is my Khan.
쿠툴룬은 나이가 들수록
더 맹렬해지는군요
Khutulun has grown more fierce with age.
더 아름다워지고요
And more beautiful.
내 딸은 절대 남편을
얻지 못할 것 같구나!
It appears my daughter
will never take a husband!
- 딸이요?
- 아주 훌륭한 전사요
- Daughter?
- She is a prized warrior...
그 처녀성은 자신을 이긴 자에게
주기로 맹세했지
whose virginity is promised
to any man who can defeat her.
구혼자가 많아
말 20마리를 바쳐서
Suitors abound,
offering horses by the score
저 아이와 몸싸움을 해
이길 기회를 얻네
for an opportunity to wrestle and win her.
My herds have multiplied, but...
내 가축은 배로 늘었으나...
I will find Khutulun her match.
쿠툴룬에게 꼭 짝을
찾아줄 것이다
비암바 자네가
도전해 보게
You should challenge her, Byamba.
자네도 힘센 전사이지 않나
You are a powerful warrior.
I am not worthy, Kaidu.
전 그럴 만한 가치가 없습니다, 카이두
쿠툴룬이 우창의 우리 군대를
지휘했다고 생각해 보라
Imagine if Khutulun
had commanded our armies at Wuchang.
A glorious victory
she would have given our Lord.
영광스러운 승리를
칸께 바쳤을 것이네
씨름할 자가 하나 부족합니다, 황자
We are one wrestler short, Prince.
한번 해 보시겠소?
Care to test your skills?
어디 한 번...
Show us the...
그 용맹함을 보여주시오
aggression in your blood?
제가 하겠습니다
I would be honored...
Lord Kaidu.
카이두 칸
아들아
Son.
제가 아들이 맞습니까?
Am I?
위대한 칸이 그의 진정한 후계자를
욕보이시겠습니까?
I doubt the Great Khan
would humiliate his one true heir.
아니죠, 칸이시라면
그의 진정한 아들을
No, the Khan wouldn't
shame his one true son
라틴인과 사생아와 함께
연회에 참석하게 하진 않으실...
by leaving him to attend a feast
with a Latin and a bastard whose...
계속 하세요!
Go on!
절 죽이십시오
Kill me.
내 숙부인 우구데이가
큰 병을 앓을 때...
When my uncle, g?梨ei,
became gravely ill...
의원과 주술사들은...
the healers and shamans...
혼령들을 달래기 위해...
thought they could appease the spirits...
양과 수퇘지와 수사슴을
제물로 바치라 했다
by sacrificing goats, boars and stags.
하지만 숙부의 병은
점점 깊어져 갔지
But g?梨ei's illness just grew worse.
그래서 여자와...
So, they tried offering women...
거지와 소작농들을
바치려 했다
beggars and peasants.
소용이 없었지
Nothing.
그리고 조정의 신하를
바치려 했다
Then men from the court.
그래도 병은 더 깊어졌지
Still, his illness increased.
그리고 사경을 헤매게 되자
And soon, when he was at death's door...
그가 가장 신뢰하는
주술사가...
his most trusted shaman determined that...
그의 병을 고치는 방법은
가족을 희생하는 것이라 말했다
the only way to cure him was...
to sacrifice a member of his family.
내 아버님인 툴루이가...
My father, Tolui...
volunteered.
자원했지
아버님이 독배를 마시고
돌아가시자마자
He drank from the poisoned cup
and when he died...
숙부는 일어나셨다
g?梨ei rose from his bed.
아들아, 그 이야기는
That, son, was a tale
아버님의 체면을
살리기 위해 만들어진 것이다
conjured to save Tolui's face.
체면을 잃는다...
Losing face.
네가 배우고 경험한...
Chinese concept you've been taught...
한족의 개념이다
and have experienced.
사실은... 아버님은
약한 사람이었다
Truth is... Father was a weak man.
Screwing whores
and drinking airag till his liver burst.
오입질을 일삼고
간이 터질 때까지 술을 마셨다
몽골의 왕좌를
이을 자격이 없었다
He never deserved to
occupy the Mongol throne.
명예
Honor...
그런 건 없었다
he had none.
용기?
Courage...
그런 건 도박장에
쏟아부었지
he spent it at the gaming houses.
아직도 내 귓가엔 그분이
불평하는 소리가 들린다
I still hear his whining in my ear.
너도 여인네처럼
불평하고 있다
You, too, whine like a woman.
칸이 될 자라면...
A man who would be Khan
must stand tall and crush those
who dare mock him.
자신만만히 서서 그를 놀리는
자들을 쳐부수어야 한다
모르시겠습니까?
You don't see?
제가 여인네처럼
불평한다면
If I whine like a woman...
아버님께서 저를 이렇게
만드셨기 때문이라는 것을요
it is because you molded me that way.
저들이 날 놀리는 것은
제가 한족처럼 생각하고
They mock me because I think Chinese...
한족처럼 행동하기 때문입니다!
because I act Chinese!
아버님께서 저를 한족처럼...!
Because you made me Chinese...
너는 한족 학자들에게
교육을 받았지만
You were taught by Chinese scholars.
그렇다고 몽골인이
아닌 것은 아니다!
That does not make you less Mongol.
그렇게 행동하라!
You act it...
아니면 내가 널 죽일 것이다
or I will kill you.
후궁이 수백 명이라던데
I hear he has hundreds of consorts.
난 수천 명이라 들었어
I hope he has thousands.
일 년에 한 번 들어가는
것만으로도 난 충분해
Being mounted once a year
is more than enough for me.
그분의 것 크기가
말의 것 만하다던데
Daiyu says his cock
is like that of a horse.
그럼 귀리나 먹이고
난 놔뒀으면 좋겠어
Then feed it oats and leave me alone.
국자?
A ladle?
Your cousin said it was made by
the greatest artisan in India.
폐하의 오촌이 인도의 위대한
장인이 만든 것이라 했습니다
From the ball sack of an elephant.
코끼리의 고환으로
만든 것이 아니냐
장식용을 만든 것일수도 있지요
Perhaps it is meant to be ornamental.
그리고?
And?
진정한 몽골 문화에 대한
네 생각은 어떠하냐?
What were your thoughts
on true Mongol culture?
아라그 맛은 어떻더냐?
How was the airag?
마실 만하였습니다
It was enjoyable.
그 말밖에 나오지 않느냐?
Is that the only word you can conjure?
꽤 마실 만하였습니다
Highly enjoyable.
Hmm.
그래?
나에 대해 어떻게 말하더냐?
How did they speak of me?
존경심을 담아 말하였습니다
With respect.
폐하의 위대함에 걸맞게요
Befitting one of your magnitude.
그래
Hmm.
그럼 내 아들은?
And my son?
Did they afford him similar esteem?
나를 존경하는 것만큼
아들을 존중하더냐?
대칸의 아들로서
존중받았습니다
He was shown the honor
due the son of the Great Khan.
Describe for me what you saw, Latin...
그대가 본 것을 말하라, 라틴인
있는 그대로
as you saw it.
거짓말은...
A lie...
죄없는 목숨을 죽일 수 있다
can cost innocent lives.
우구데이 가의 사람들이
쿠빌라이의 아들을
A lie about how the House of g?梨ei...
어찌 대접하였는지
거짓말하는 것이...
treats the son of Kublai...
이 제국 전체를 위험에
빠뜨릴 수 있단 말이다!
endangers this entire Empire!
그런 거짓말은
벌을 받아야 한다
Such lies should be punished.
안됩니다, 폐하!
No. Sire, no!
내가 이자를 그냥 보낸다면
Well, if I let him walk away,
일주일 뒤 술을 한 잔 걸치고
이리 말할 것이다
he will have his wine
six nights from now and say...
칸께서 하찮은 외국인이
거짓말을 하였는데도 놓아주셨다
"Khan was lied to by a lowly foreigner
and gave that liar his leave."
이자는 너의 죄를 나눠가졌다
He shares your sin now.
네놈의 희생양인 것이다
He is your scapegoat.
가라, 라틴인
술이 깨게 자도록 해라
Go, Latin. Sleep off the drink.
Sync & corrections by Elderfel
www.addic7ed.com